Inventory of the Powell Family Papers 1775-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers of the Powell Family, 1785-1927, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1850-1859. (Box 1-2)
    - Papers, 1857., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 9 December 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports of Nina getting her teeth straightened; describes method; reports that the number of scarlet fever cases is greatly reduced; she is very busy with the boarding school; tells of a fight between Charlie McCormick and a police officer; mentions Hunter Holmes McGuire; family news.
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "daughter" [Nina Powell] n.p., n.d. [1857?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Discusses the death of Robert[?] and the reaction of the town; gives news of friends; sends her love to her mother and relatives; wants to know what Dr. Chase said about her teeth.
      - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, n.p., to Nina [Powell], n.p., n.d. [1857?]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Writes about Nina's plans to go home; says she is concerned about her traveling when her teeth are in such a condition.
    - Papers, 1858, 20 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell], Winchester, Virginia, 17 January 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to the general "hard times" everyone is experiencing; describes farm activities; much family news; describes how to make a mousetrap.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Mother," [Selina Lloyd Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 22 January [18]58., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Describes midwest weather and the usual fall-like temperatures; says that they are all much healthier because of the mild weather; says ties are hard and the bank in Henry just closed, but that the town is continuing to improve; asks about Mrs. Powell's occupation, teaching; mentions the death of Rob[er]t Conrad and describes his character; messages to family members.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell], Winchester, [Virginia], 1 March 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports of freezing temperatures of -15 F and snow in Henry; mentions of sleighing in the snow; reports story of a bank robbery.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to "Father," [Charles L. Powell, Sr.], [Winchester, Virginia], 15 March [18]58., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports of Lloyd's [Powell] trip to St. Louis to try and find Charles a job; much family news; mentions a Mr. Lombard who plans to return to Henry and open a bank of issue.
      - Lloyd Powell, aboard steamer J. C. Swon[?] at Cairo, Illinois, to "Sister" [Hattie Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 28 March [18]58., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses who owes him letters from home; says he could not find a job for Charley [Charles L. Powell, Jr.?] in St. Louis because of the poor economy; gives news of Randolph Powell, of St. Louis, and John Webb Powell, of Utah; says he will be home during the summer.
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 3 April 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Mentions that she missed his birthday with a card but thought of him that day; expresses religious feelings and beliefs; family news; lists people recently confirmed in the Church; outbreak of typhus fever at the University[?].
      - Lloyd Powell, Mobile, Alabama, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 22 April [18]58., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Tells of his travels; describes Memphis, Tennessee; gives news of "cousin" Will[ia]m Powell who resides in Memphis; gives news of Mr. And Mrs. Mason, residing in Vicksburg; describes Leake County where he sold some of his Uncle Nelson's land; gives news of "cousin" john Wilson of New Orleans and of "cousin" John Chilton, who may send his daughter Sarah to school in Virginia; tells his travel plans, stating he will be in Virginia in a month; gives news to family and friends.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 10 May 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Describes scenery where he is; tells of a May party that some school girls had; describes his boat riding trip; family news; mentions arrival of Mr. Winn, the new Presbyterian minister.
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia] to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 6 July 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports having been sick with a bad cold; much family news; Nina has problems with other schoolgirls because her parents operate the school; trying to plan Charlie's return home for the summer.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 7 July 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Asks about fourth of July entertainment; Mr. Winn gave an exceptional sermon; Uncle Richard[?] bought a piano and a side-saddle; family news.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 27 August 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Inquires about boarding students; inquires about vacations at Capon [Springs, West Virginia]; tells of his success at duck hunting; family news; mentions [Stephen A.] Douglas.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Mother" [Selina Lloyd Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 29 August [18]58., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Gives news of Uncle R[ichard]'s and Uncle Fred's families; says that Frank's baby is still ill; gives news of Hammond and Min[na]; comments that he will not see his family for another year; gives news of Charlie [Charles L. Powell, Jr.] and his employment possibilities; asks about Uncle Neb of Clark, [Virginia?].
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 26 September 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Gives her opinion about chewing tobacco, smoking, and other bad habits; incorporates religious duty into her opinion; some family news.
      - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to Charlie [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], n.p., 28 September [1858?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses his habit of chewing tobacco and how he should discipline himself to quit.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Sister" [Hattie Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 20 October 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses the weather; reports on Hammond; reports that Mr. Chandler of Henry is getting married in Boston; says they will stay at Mrs. Taber's for the winter; gives news of Charlie [Charles L. Powell, Jr.]; comments on the involvement of women in politics in Henry; news of friends; comments on the decreased enrollment at the family school, saying they will at least have a lighter workload; mentions Stephen A. Douglas.
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 28 October 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Expresses her disappointment in Charlie's having tasted tobacco; tells him that he is doing wrong to continue this habit; voices many religious views.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 5 December 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports that river is flooding the town; talks of Christmas holidays; family news.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 16 December 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        A birthday letter for Nina's sixteenth birthday; describes the weather; much family news; Min[?] is the "editress" of the "Minnehaha"; tells of the affairs of a Miss Amanda[?].
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to "mother," [Selina Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 19 December 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Gives account of how he spends his days with emphasis on his Sunday activities; tried to quit chewing tobacco but couldn't; tells of episode where Uncle Richard[?] lost his saddle bags in the town of Bradford; river was frozen and people are ice skating; family news.
      - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to Charlie, Charles Powell, Jr., [Henry, Illinois], [December 1856-58]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Tells where the girls boarding with them are going for Christmas; describes their Christmas plans; recollects their last Christmas with Minna; gives religious advice; sends her love to Lloyd.
    - Papers, 1859., 18 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      - Johns Hopkins, Balti[more], [Maryland], to "Cousin Rebecca," Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 10 January 1859., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Would love for her to stay with him; mentions a sister Hannah.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina L. Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 13 February 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that Lloyd [Powell] and Uncle Richard[?] have gone to Memphis, [Tennessee]; tells of the building of a road for $10,000; describes a surprise party he attended; mentions Valentine's Day and how many he has received; family news.
      - Lloyd Powell, Memphis, Tennessee, to "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 13 February [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that Uncle Richard and Frank are with him in Memphis, to see if they want to move there; says that he does not believe Uncle Richard will leave Illinois, but that Frank probably will; says that they tried to look up W[illia]m Powell but he had moved to Arkansas; discusses the possibilities of his parents establishing a school in the area, and the risks involved.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Father" [Charles L. Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 19 March [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Gives news of Uncle Richard and Uncle Fred; says Uncle Fred and Frank will close their business and leave Henry; tells of a conversation with Bishop Otey of Memphis on the subject of establishing a girls school there; gives details of the proposal in case his father is interested; gives news of the private school situation in Arkansas; reports on his business dealings in Arkansas; discusses financial matters.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 7 April [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Gives news of Uncle Fred who has been ill; says that the women of the town are all inspecting the new spring goods brought in from Saint Louis; discusses his daily schedule; says Charlie [Charles L. Powell, Jr.] is in singing school; asks about Nina's walks and lectures on the benefits of exercise to health and appearance.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 22 May [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Describes spring in Illinois; inquires about relatives in Alexandria; comments on Uncle Nelson's helpless state; discusses the chances of recovering Uncle Nelson's lands in Arkansas; describes the area of Henry where the family used to live; comments that she now weights 108 " lbs., which is more than her daughters weigh; sends his love to Grand Ma Powell, Aunt Ann, and Uncle Neb.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina L. Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 5 June 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        A baby girl was born who is Nina's cousin [Uncle Richard's daughter?]; describes a fishing trip; mentions finding several Indian graves with skeletons and other items; tells story of a "mad" dog who bit many people.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Sister" [Hattie L. Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 13 June [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Gives news of Illinois relatives; describes a trip that he and Uncle Richard took through Stark County, emphasizing the changes that have taken place in the last five years; comments on Charley's [Charles L. Powell, Jr.] development into a young man; reports that Uncle Richard will leave the land business on September 1st; discusses his involvement in the business and his desire to visit Virginia.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Sister" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 10 July [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Expresses his relief that his brother Charles arrived safely in Virginia; comments on how scattered the family is at present; mentions Cousin Fanny Cochran's wedding in Middleburg, [Virginia]; discusses Mr. Hyde's trip in the "aerial vessel" Atlantic from St. Louis to New York, as reported in the "Republican"; reports that Frank has another son, Horatio Nelson; news of other Illinois relatives; describes the July 4 festivities.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Father" [Charles L. Powell], [Leesburg, Virginia], 23 July [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discusses an unprofitable year for his business; discusses a business proposition made to his brother Charles and Harry and Benton Janney by Uncle Richard, concerning the opening of the store; gives news of Illinois relatives; comments that his Uncle Richard, who just turned 43, may begin to use his middle name again and become Richard H. Lloyd; comments on how, in the past twenty years, the Powell family has spread from "New York to Salt Lake City, and from the 'Lakes' to the Gulf of Mexico."
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell], n.p., 8 August [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that Uncle Richard, Min[na] will stop at Fulton County to visit relatives; gives his opinion about Minna not returning to Winchester [Virginia] for school, stating that she has become too undisciplined and used to complete freedom in Illinois to be effectively taught in a school; describes Frank's son Horatio Nelson; comments on the family's health, saying that his father [Charles L. Powell] weights twenty pounds more than he does and his mother [Selina L. Powell] weighs only six pounds less, and also weighs more than any of her three brothers in Illinois; asks her if she is finished school and will make her debut.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 11 September [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that Charley [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], Harry and Benton [Janney] have begun their business named "H and TB Janney and Co."; asks about the boarding school and discusses the difficulties of running one; reports that Frank's family and Mrs. Hammond[?] are on their way to Memphis to live; reports that Uncle Fred is planning an extended visit to Virginia, and then will probably move to Memphis; says he and Uncle Richard dissolved their partnership and that Uncle Richard plans to move to Memphis as well; reports that crops are poor, so his business will be slow; plans to see them for Christmas.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Sister" [Rebecca, Hattie, or Nina Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 18 September [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that there is a County Fair next week; describes in detail an incident of a burning well; expresses sorrow that the family school will be so small this year; reports that the 'W S Fair' in Chicago is now over.
      - H. and T. B. Janney and Co., Henry, Illinois, to Miss Nina L. Powell, [Henry, Illinois?], 27 September 1859., 1 page. PM. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discussing fall and winter goods being stocked at "Lloyd's Big Brick" in Henry, Illinois.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Sister" [Nina Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 30 October [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Much family news; mentions marriage of Miss Hutchins, and deaths of 2 children of Mrs. Clara Ferguson; received invitation to wedding of "Miss Mittie"; gives his opinion of marriage.
      - S[elina Lloyd] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie" [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry], [Illinois], 29 November 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        A french teacher at the boarding school died; mentions excitement due to 'John' Browne's execution and that there are 26 companies of soldiers at Charlestown, [West Virginia]; mentions growing discontent of slaves; describes how men have loaded pistols ready in their homes; tells how many people are being imprisoned; tells of other strains between North and South; some family news; mentions [Robert Young] Conrad.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 2 December 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Reports that Uncle Richard's baby has been christened Elizabeth Jenkins [Lloyd]; comments that this is the day that [John] Brown is to be executed; comments on the number of arrests in Virginia of strangers traveling through the state.
        Including newspaper clipping, n.d., of a poem about infants.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "mother," [Selina L. Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 20 December [18]59., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discusses Professors Wise and LaMountain's attempt to establish daily balloon transportation from the "western" states to the East Coast; family news; says he is anxious for the family in Illinois to move southward; mentions the execution of "Cook and his confederates" [involved in John Brown's attempted insurrection] on December 16.
  - Papers, 1860-1869. (Box 2-3)
    - Papers, 1860., 17 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      - Mary L. Boice, Henry, [Illinois], to Lloyd Powell, [Henry, Illinois], 2 February [18]60., 1 page. ANS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Invitation to a "Leap Year" party.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois] to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 6 February 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Mentions and encloses invitation to a "Leap Year" party; describes events at the party; describes weather and reports of a sleighing party; reports marriage of Mary Ann Hoyt, friend of the family.
        Including ANS from Maggie J. Richmond, Henry, [Illinois], to Charles [L.] Powell, [Jr.],[Henry, Illinois], [February 1860], inviting him to a "Leap Year" party.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Mother" [Selina Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 16 February [18]60., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Talks about Uncle Richard's[?] baby girl; gives report of Charles L. Powell and some family news.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to Nina L. Powell, Loudoun County, Virginia, 14 March [18]60., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses "spring fever" concerning work; describes weather; speaks of Uncle Nelson's Lloyd death and how it should be a happy time; thanks his father for "Alex[andria] Gazettes" containing articles about the Whig convention; much family news.
      - [Selina Lloyd Powell], Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Carles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 21 March 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Writes about her feelings during the time following her brother Nelson's death; recounts the last days she spent with Nelson Lloyd.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Father", [Charles L. Powell, Sr., Winchester, Virginia], 14 April 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Talks about assessed value of some land or property and makes reference to Lloyd Brothers and Co.; speaks of crops and the effects of the weather; mentions how road being finished would provide trade with those on the other side of the river; township will vote on how to acquire additional funds to complete the road; mentions the whig convention and how they now represent such a small minority of people.
      - Rebecca C. Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to Charles [L. Powell], n.p., 24 April [18]60., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Talks of spring dresses and bonnets; mentions hearing address by William McDonald; discusses opening of a shoe and book manufactory; speaks of beating "the Yankees with their own men"; family news; religious advice; mentions use of telegraph.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Sister," [Virginia], 18 May 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses agriculture and effects of weather on crops; talks of visiting New England and of dislike of their attitudes; expresses extreme negative opinion of Yankees.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell], Winchester, Virginia, 22 July [1860]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Family news; mentions work at the store; discusses events around town.
        Including [poem?] written in Latin on both sides of envelope. Locks of hair also enclosed.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Mother" [Selina (Lloyd) Powell, Winchester, Virginia], 30 July [18]60., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses crops and agriculture; describes Illinois scenery; family news; inquires about trip to Capron [Springs]; mentions "Uncle Richard's" card selling tour.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 26 August [18]60., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses Congressional race; mentions Cassius M. Clay of Kentucky and his visit to Illinois; talks about rise in crime; family news.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to "sister," n.p., 28 October 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses confusion about having joined the church; religious discussion; some family and neighborhood news.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "sister" [Rebecca Powell, Winchester, Virginia], 16 November [18]60., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Inquires about trip to New England; mentions "Alexandria Sentinel"; family news.
      - S[elina Lloyd] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie" [Charles L. Powell, Jr., Henry, Illinois], 3 December [1860]., 11 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses climate and busy season of Christmas; debates issue of [Civil War] and effects; gives religious advice; family news; [Robert Young] Conrad.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Father" [Charles L. Powell, Sr., Winchester, Virginia], 11 December [18]60., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses problems due to political and financial situation of the country; talks about boils on his hand; family news; mentions kindness of Mayor Turner.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 16 December 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Nina's eighteenth birthday; discusses the weather; talks about sleighing and skating; mentions " Pickwick Papers"; describes hunting interest; makes reference to several literary works.
    - Papers, 1861., 35 items. (Box-folder 2:5-6)
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to "sister," n.p., [?] January 1861., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Talks of trade being slow; election of a Mr. McFadden as "Justice of the Peace"; mentions sleighing and the weather; describes hayride in snow and people he went with.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Father" [Charles L. Powell, Sr., Winchester, Virginia], 14 January 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Discusses his indebtedness to his father and his financial situation.
      - Lloyd Powell, [Henry, Illinois], to [Charles L. Powell, Sr., Winchester, Virginia], 15 January [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Discusses political situation and "imminent danger of civil war"; comments on government involvement and troops in a war; mentions social life.
      - Catharine Powell, "Bellvue", [Loudoun County, Virginia.?], to "son," [Charles L. Powell, Sr., Winchester, Virginia], 20 January 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)